Welcome, brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹 歴史的瞬間へようこそ！
This is a historic moment!
Our studio has moved
and is now located only minutes
スタジオが ニューヨーク州
ウォーウィックの新しい世界本部から—
from the new world headquarters complex
at Warwick, New York.
ほど近くに移動しました
And this first program
from our new studio
新しいスタジオでの
最初のプログラムから—
will bring you
many spiritual gems.
たくさんの霊的宝石をお届けします
First, what obstacles
have been overcome
まず どんな障害を乗り越えて—
so that common people
can read God’s Word?
一般の人たちが神の言葉を読めるように
なったでしょうか？
In this exciting documentary,
we will see the courage shown
英国のウィリアム・ティンダルが
示した勇気についての—
興奮を誘う
ドキュメンタリーです
by William Tyndale of England.
What helped two fierce enemies
かつて憎み合っていた二人が
親友になれたのは なぜでしょうか？
to become close friends?
The uniting power
of the Bible is evident
この話から 聖書の一致させる力が
分かるでしょう
in this account.
And what can we learn
from the apostle Paul
宣教で進歩するため
使徒パウロから何を学べるでしょうか？
that will improve our ministry?
We will find out as we join this family
晩の家族の崇拝に参加しましょう
during their Family Worship evening.
では 1月のJW Broadcastingです！
This is the January program
of JW Broadcasting!
As Jehovah’s Witnesses,
we truly love the Bible.
わたしたちは エホバの証人として
聖書を本当に大切にしています
Why?
なぜですか？
Because we know it is God’s Word.
聖書は神の言葉だからです
That’s why we love reading it,
we love studying it,
それゆえ 聖書を読み 学び
その歴史を喜んで調べるのです
and we love learning about its history.
When we pause
for a moment and reflect on
少し立ち止まって—
過去幾世紀にもわたってなされて来た
聖書を妨害し—
the many efforts that have been made
through the centuries
その頒布さえも阻止しようとした
多くの試みについて考えると—
to hinder and even stop
the distribution of the Bible,
it becomes obvious
that its Author, Jehovah,
次のことは明らかです
それは その著者である
エホバ神ご自身が—
has been personally involved
in preserving
その貴重な言葉を保存し 知らせることに
関与しておられたということです
and making known
his precious Word.
This is very much
in harmony with the thought
これはイザヤ 40章8節の言葉と
見事に調和しています
in Isaiah 40:8:
“The green grass dries up,
“青草は干からび 花は枯れた”
“the blossom withers,
“しかし わたしたちの神の言葉は
定めのない時に至るまで保つのである”
but the word
of our God endures forever.”
With that in mind,
この点を念頭に置いて—
I’m happy to speak
with you this month
今月はわたしがいつも
心にかけている事柄をお話しします
on a theme
that’s very close to my heart:
主題は
“神の言葉は永久に存続する”です
“The Word of Our God Endures Forever.”
The more we come to appreciate
the value of God’s Word,
わたしたちは神の言葉の価値を
認識すればするほど—
the more we’ll be moved to read it
それをもっと読みたいと
願うようになり—
and, even more important,
to apply it in our lives.
さらに重要なことに それを生活に
当てはめるようになります
エホバ神は人に霊感を与えて—
Jehovah gave us an outstanding gift
when he inspired
ご自分の貴重な言葉を
書き記させたとき—
faithful men
to record his precious Word.
貴重な贈り物を与えてくださいました
It’s through the pages of God’s Word
書き記された神の言葉を通してのみ—
that we learn
just how much God loves us.
わたしたちは神の愛の深さについて
学べるのです
Thus, his Word contains
guidance on how to live.
その言葉は生きていくための
道しるべです
It outlines his purpose
in creating us.
それには 人を創造した目的が
記されています
It gives us his precious promises
for life everlasting
平和と幸福の内に得られる—
永遠の命の貴重な神の約束が
記されています
in peace and happiness.
No wonder the apostle Paul
was inspired to write
使徒パウロが テモテ第二 3章16, 17節で
霊感の下に記したことは当を得ています
at 2 Timothy 3:16, 17:
“All Scripture is inspired of God
“聖書全体は神の霊感を受けたもので—”
“and beneficial for teaching,
for reproving,
“教え 戒め 物事を正し
義にそって訓育するのに有益です”
“for setting things straight,
for disciplining in righteousness,
“so that the man of God
may be fully competent,
“それは 神の人が十分な能力を備え—”
“あらゆる良い業に対して
全く整えられた者となるためです”
completely equipped for every good work.”
Of course, Satan the Devil
does not want people to have access
むろんサタン悪魔は
人々が天の父エホバからの—
to these precious truths
from our heavenly Father, Jehovah.
この貴重な真理に接することを
望んでいません
It’s no surprise
that there have been many obstacles
聖書の入手を困難にする多くの障害が
あったのもうなずけます
to making the Bible available.
While Satan may not have been
directly behind all of these,
サタンが背後でそのすべてを
操っていたわけではないものの—
he certainly
has made use of them.
それらを利用したことは明らかです
What are some
of these obstacles,
どんな障害が どのように
克服されてきたのでしょうか？
and how have they been overcome?
Let’s consider the first obstacle:
最初に 言語という障壁について
考えましょう
language barriers.
The first 39 books of the Bible,
旧約聖書とも呼ばれる
聖書の最初の39冊の書は—
which are often called the Old Testament,
were written primarily
in the Hebrew language.
主にヘブライ語で書かれました
These books were known
これらの書はヘブライ語を話す
エホバの僕たちによって知られていました
by Hebrew-speaking servants of Jehovah.
However, as time went on,
しかし 時の経過と共に
とりわけバビロン滅亡後に—
particularly after
the destruction of Babylon,
ユダヤ人の多くは他の国民の中に
自分たちの共同体を作りました
many Jews established communities
in other nations of the earth.
Many of these Jews spoke Greek.
その多くはギリシャ語を話し
もはやヘブライ語を用いなくなりました
They no longer used Hebrew.
That meant that many Jews
no longer had access
それは 理解できる言語で
聖書に接することが—
to the Scriptures in a language
they could understand.
もはやできなくなったという意味です
Consider what had happened.
次に何が生じましたか？
As Alexander the Great conquered
アレクサンドロス大王が
当時の世界を次々と征服していった結果—
more and more
of the then-known world,
Greek gradually became
ギリシャ語は徐々にその帝国内で
商業と政治の共通語となっていきました
the common language
of commerce and government
throughout his empire.
If the Bible
was to be understood
ギリシャ語を話す
広大な地域に散在しているユダヤ人や—
by the Jews and by Jewish proselytes
ユダヤ教に改宗した人たちに
聖書が理解されるためには—
who were scattered throughout
this vast Greek-speaking territory,
ギリシャ語に翻訳される
必要がありました
it needed to be translated into Greek.
Beginning in about the year 250 B.C.E.,
西暦前250年ごろから—
ヘブライ語聖書はギリシャ語に
翻訳されるようになりました
the Hebrew Scriptures began
to be translated into Greek.
In time, that Greek translation
came to be known
やがてそのギリシャ語訳は—
セプトゥアギンタ訳
として知られるようになりました
as the Septuagint.
It was widely and frequently used
by the Christians
それは 西暦1世紀にギリシャ語を話す
クリスチャンたちによって—
in the first century who spoke Greek.
広く頻繁に用いられました
In fact, the writers
of the Christian Greek Scriptures,
実際 クリスチャン・ギリシャ語聖書
つまり新約聖書の筆者たちは—
which is often called
the New Testament,
frequently quoted directly
from that translation.
その翻訳から頻繁に直接引用しました
このようにして
その障害は克服されました
So that obstacle had been overcome.
But there were many more
language obstacles ahead.
しかし さらに多くの
言語の障壁がありました
As the Roman Empire
began to flourish,
ローマ帝国が繁栄するようになると—
ギリシャ語に代わってラテン語が
共通語になりました
Latin replaced Greek
as a common language.
Now it was necessary
to translate the Bible into Latin.
今度は 聖書をラテン語に翻訳する
必要が生じました
Some Latin translations
of the Bible books began to appear.
ラテン語の聖書翻訳が
いくつか登場するようになりました
But it was in the year 405 C.E.
that Jerome completed
しかし ヒエロニムスがラテン語の
聖書全体の翻訳を完成したのは—
the definitive Latin translation
of the Bible.
西暦405年のことでした
It came to be known
それはラテン語ウルガタ訳として
知られるようになりました
as the Latin Vulgate.
Jerome’s translation
would become
ヒエロニムスの翻訳は
次の千年あまりの期間—
the standard Bible
used by Christendom
キリスト教世界において
標準聖書となりました
for the next nearly 1,000 years.
However, Latin soon became
the language of the learned and the elite,
しかし ラテン語はすぐに
教育のあるエリートの言語となったため—
so the common people
could no longer understand
一般の人々は聖書の音信を
もはや理解できなくなりました
the Bible’s message.
During that long period,
there were sincere men
その長い期間のうちに—
聖書の一部を 他のいくつかの言語で
翻訳した誠実な人々がいました
that translated portions of the Bible
into some additional languages,
but these translations were,
of course, all made by hand.
しかし それらの翻訳はもちろん
すべて手書きによるものでした
Such handwritten copies of the Bible
were rare and expensive.
そうした手書きの聖書は
数が少なく高価でした
Therefore,
access to the Bible in vernacular,
ですから 自分の言語あるいは
一般の言語で読める聖書の数は—
or common languages,
was very limited.
非常に限られていました
But language was not
the only obstacle
しかし 言語だけが神の言葉の進展を脅かす
唯一の障害だったわけではありません
that threatened to prevent
the distribution of God’s Word.
Consider a second factor:
2つ目の要素があります
direct opposition
to Bible translation and distribution
それは聖書の翻訳と頒布に対する
宗教指導者の直接の反対です
from religious leaders.
That opposition
started to increase in 1229
その反対は1229年
トゥールーズの宗教会議において—
when the local church
Council of Toulouse decreed:
地元の教会が次の布告をした時から
増し加わりました
“We prohibit also
that the laity should be permitted
“我々はまた平信徒が旧約および
新約聖書を持つことを禁じる”
to have the books
of the Old or the New Testament.”
1234年にタラゴナ教会会議は
こう布告しました
In 1234,
the Council of Tarragona decreed:
“No one should possess the books
of the Old or the New Testament
“何人たりとも自国語で旧約 および
新約聖書を所有してはならない”
“in the vernacular [language],
“and if anyone possesses them,
“もし所有している者がいるなら—”
“let him deliver them, within eight days
“この布告の発令から8日以内に
それらを地元の司教に提出させ—”
“from the promulgation of this decree,
“それらを焼き払うように”
to the local bishop,
so that they may be burned.”
Thus, during
a very long period in history,
こうして歴史上
非常に長い期間にわたって—
there was limited access to the Bible
一般の人々の話す言語で聖書を読むことは
ほとんどできなかったのです
in the languages
spoken by common people.
But did that mean
that the Word of God
しかし それは神の言葉がずっと
存続できないという意味でしょうか？
would not continue to endure?
Neither language barriers
言語の障壁も
宗教指導者たちの反対も—
nor opposition from religious leaders
神の言葉が広く知られるのを
阻止することはできませんでした
could stop God’s Word
from being made known.
Even in those dark times,
そうした暗黒時代にあっても
神の言葉を愛し それを懸命に翻訳し—
there were individuals
who loved God’s Word
and who worked hard
to translate it
人々がそれを入手できるように
した者たちがいたのです
and to make it available to others.
Consider John Wycliffe
ジョン・ウィクリフとロラード派と
呼ばれるその追随者たちがいます
and his followers
who were called the Lollards.
John Wycliffe and his associates
ジョン・ウィクリフとその仲間たちは
1382年ごろ英訳聖書を完成しました
completed the translation
of the Bible
into English
about the year 1382.
They eagerly
hand copied the translation
翻訳した聖書の手書きのコピーを
熱心に作成し—
and then traveled
from village to village
村から村を回わり
人々に聖書を読んだのです
reading the Bible
to the common people.
Despite tremendous opposition
from the church,
教会のすさまじい反対にもかかわらず
ウィクリフと追随者たちは—
Wycliffe and his followers
made the Bible available
心の正直な多くの人々が
英語で聖書を入手できるようにしたのです
to many honesthearted people
in the English language.
After Wycliffe died in 1384,
1384年のウィクリフの死後—
その追随者たちには
厳しい反対が臨みました
great opposition
came to his followers.
Many had land
and property confiscated.
多くの者たちの土地や所有物は没収され
火あぶりにされた人もいました
Others were burned
at the stake.
In response to the work
of Wycliffe and the Lollards,
ウィクリフとロラード派の
行なったことに対応して—
in 1408,
1408年 カンタベリーの大司教であった
トマス･アランデルはこう述べました
Thomas Arundel,
Archbishop of Canterbury, declared:
“We therefore decree and ordain
“したがって我々は
次のことを布告し 定める”
“that no man shall, hereafter,
by his own authority,
“今後は何人も自らの権威で 聖書本文を
英語や他の言語に翻訳してはならない”
“translate any text of the Scripture
“into English,
or any other tongue,
. . . upon pain
of greater excommunication.”
“そうする者は破門の痛みが伴うであろう”
Did such opposition
wipe out efforts
このような反対は聖書を翻訳し広める
努力を一掃してしまったでしょうか？
to translate and make
the Bible available?
Absolutely not!
そのようなことはありません！
The work of Wycliffe
and his associates
ウィクリフと追随者たちの働きは
英国や中央ヨーロッパにおいてさえ—
stimulated interest in the Bible
throughout England
and even as far as central Europe.
聖書への関心を高める結果となりました
Religious leaders were not able
to silence the Word of God.
宗教指導者たちは神の言葉を
沈黙させることはできませんでした
In fact, within just a few decades
after Wycliffe’s death,
事実 ウィクリフの死後
わずか数十年たった後—
two factors
led to a tremendous increase
聖書が驚異的に広まるのに役立った
２つの要素が生じました
in the availability
of the Bible.
最初のものは1454年ごろに—
The first,
about the year 1454,
組み替えできる活字を用いた
印刷技術が発達したことです
was the development
of printing with movable type.
This invention would
in time allow for the printing
この発明によって多くの言語で
大量の聖書を印刷できるようになりました
of large quantities
of Bibles in many languages.
The second factor was
the compiling and printing
2番目の要素はヘブライ語および
ギリシャ語原文による聖書本文の—
of the Hebrew and Greek
original language text
収集と印刷が行なわれたことです
of the Holy Scriptures.
This allowed many translators
これにより多くの翻訳者たちは
原文で聖書本文を入手できるようになり—
to have access
to the original language texts
so that they then could produce
自分たちの言語で質の高い翻訳を
行なえるようになりました
high-quality translations
in their own languages.
What was the result?
その結果は？
In the 1500’s across Europe,
1500年代にはヨーロッパ中で
新しい翻訳が行なわれ—
fresh translations
were made and printed
一般の人々の言語で印刷されたのです
in vernacular,
or common languages,
それらは ドイツ語 英語 イタリア語
フランス語 オランダ語 チェコ語—
including German, English, Italian, French,
Dutch, Czech, Danish, Swedish,
デンマーク語 スウェーデン語—
Spanish, Slovenian, and many others.
スペイン語 スロベニア語
その他多くあります
However, opposition continued.
しかし 反対は続きました
Bible translators were frequently hounded
by the Inquisition,
聖書翻訳者たちは異端審問によって
たびたび追い回され—
and some translators like
William Tyndale and John Rogers
ウィリアム・ティンダルや
ジョン・ロジャーズのように—
殺害された翻訳者たちもいます
were even put to death
for their work.
Nonetheless, the Word of God
continued to endure
にもかかわらず
神の言葉は引き続き存続し—
and be made available
to more and more language groups.
ますます多くの言語で
入手できるようになりました
By the early 1800’s,
1800年代の初期までに
聖書翻訳は勢いを増し加えはじめました
Bible translation
began to speed up.
Bible societies
and intrepid translators
聖書協会や勇敢な翻訳者たちは
地の様々な場所で仕事を始め—
began to work
in many parts of the earth
so that the Bible began
to appear in languages
やがてアジア アフリカ
太平洋の島々の言語で—
of Asia, Africa,
the Pacific islands,
また アメリカ大陸の土着の言語でも
聖書が読めるようになりました
as well as in indigenous languages
of the Americas.
From 1800 to 1899,
1800年から1899年にかけて
聖書の一部が400の言語に翻訳され—
some portions of the Bible
were translated
into some 400 languages,
1900年から1950年にかけて
さらに500以上の言語が加えられました
and from 1900 to 1950,
more than 500 languages
were added.
Consider what has been accomplished
with the New World Translation.
「新世界訳聖書」が成し遂げたこと
について考えてみてください
As of this month,
the New World Translation
今月までに「新世界訳聖書」は—
has been produced
in whole or in part
その全部あるいは一部が
149の言語で出版され—
in 149 languages,
with an additional
37 languages approved.
さらに 37の言語が承認されています
It’s obvious
that neither language barriers
それで 言語の障壁も
宗教指導者の反対も—
nor opposition
from religious leaders
神の言葉の頒布を阻止できなかった
ことは明らかです
was able to stop
the distribution of God’s Word.
Jehovah has protected it
through the ages.
エホバが
ずっと保護してこられたのです
It’s just as Psalm 12:6, 7 says:
それは 詩編 12編6, 7節が
述べる通りです
“The sayings of Jehovah are pure;
“エホバのみことばは浄いことば—”
“they are like silver refined
in an earthen furnace,
“地の溶鉱炉で精錬され
七度純化された銀のようだ”
“purified seven times.
“エホバよ あなたご自身が
彼らを守ってくださいます”
“You will guard them, O Jehovah;
“あなたは この世代から
定めのない時に至るまで—”
“you will protect each one of them
from this generation forever.”
“ひとりびとりを
保護してくださるのです”
Yes, Jehovah
has protected each one
そうです エホバはこの時代まで—
ご自分の語られたそれぞれの
貴重な言葉を保護してこられたのです
of his precious sayings
down through the ages.
But consider a third obstacle.
では 3つ目の障害について
考えてください
Although the Bible is now available
in whole or in part
聖書は 今やおよそ3000の言語で
全体あるいはその一部が入手できますが—
in almost 3,000 languages,
many people are no longer interested
in reading it.
多くの人はそれを読むことに無関心です
In our modern age,
people have become
現代では人々はますます懐疑的になり
宗教心がありません
increasingly skeptical and irreligious.
Scientists have extolled
the theory of evolution
科学者たちは進化論を称揚し—
and have made it appear intelligent
聡明な人なら神の存在を疑うと
思い込ませています
to doubt the existence of God.
At the same time,
同時に 世の哲学は—
secular philosophy has encouraged people
自分にとって正しいと思えるところに従って
人生を決定するよう人々に勧めています
to make life decisions
according to what feels right to them.
What is the result?
結果はどうですか？
A world where people
are often guided
人々が自分の利己的で肉的な欲望に
導かれる世界の誕生です
by their own selfish, fleshly desires.
Instead of leading to happiness,
幸福になるどころか—
多くの人は空しくて
満足感のない状況にあります
many people are left
feeling empty and dissatisfied.
How is this third obstacle overcome?
この障害はどのように
克服されていますか？
Around the world,
世界中で人々は神の言葉 聖書を開き
自分でそれを読んでいます
people are opening
God’s Word, the Bible,
and reading it
for themselves.
They’re recognizing
that its thoughts
それが単なる人間の知恵から出たもの
ではないことに 人々は気付いています
are not simply human wisdom.
As they apply
its principles in their lives,
その原則を生活に当てはめることにより
満足と喜びを味わっています
they find
contentment and joy.
They develop
self-respect and dignity
創造者が示される正しい道徳規準に
従って生きることにより—
from living according to
the upright moral standards
自尊心と尊厳を保っています
outlined by our Creator.
As Psalm 119:97-100 states:
詩編 119編97-100節が
述べるとおりです
“How I do love your law!
“わたしはどんなにあなたの律法を
愛していることでしょう”
“I ponder over it all day long.
“それは一日じゅう
わたしの思いとなっています”
“Your commandment
makes me wiser than my enemies,
“あなたのおきては
わたしを敵よりも賢くし—”
“それは定めのない時に至るまで
わたしのものです”
“because it is with me forever.
“I have more insight
than all my teachers,
“すべての教師に勝る洞察力を
得るようになりました”
“because I ponder over your reminders.
“あなたの諭しが
わたしの思いとなっているからです”
“I act with more understanding
than older men,
“わたしは年長者に勝る
理解力をもって行動します”
because I observe your orders.”
“あなたの命令を守り行なったからです”
神の言葉が永久に存続することを示す
何という強力な証なのでしょう
What a powerful proof
that the Word of God endures forever.
While the advice of human philosophers
is frequently flawed,
人間の哲学者の助言には
たびたび欠陥が見つかりますが—
the Bible’s counsel works.
聖書の助言はそうではありません
If we apply it,
それを当てはめるなら—
it can help us either
to overcome or to cope
直面するかもしれない
どんな問題や状況でも—
克服したり対処したりするのに
助けとなります
with any problem
or situation that we may face.
What is more,
さらに 将来に対する神の目的が
説明されているので—
by explaining
God’s purpose for the future,
it gives us a solid hope
この地球が 当初創造されたときと
同じパラダイスに—
this earth will be restored
to the Paradise
回復されるという確かな希望を
得ることができます
that it was
when it was first created.
It will be filled
with peace and righteousness.
そこには平和と義が行き渡ります
What a wonderful gift
エホバは聖書を通して 何と素晴らしい
贈り物をくださったのでしょう！
Jehovah gave us through the Bible!
そうです 言語の障壁も
宗教指導者の反対も—
Yes, languages barriers,
opposition from religious leaders,
and even
an increasingly irreligious world
増し加わる世の無関心も
神の言葉をとどめることはできません
cannot stop God’s Word.
How can you be part
of the evidence
あなたはどのようにして神の言葉が
永久に存続することの証拠を示せますか？
that the Word of God
endures forever?
Read it every day,
study it,
毎日それを読んで 学び
そこに含まれている深い考えを黙想し—
meditate on the deep thoughts
that it contains,
and then apply
those priceless teachings in your life.
計り知れない価値を持つ
その教えを生活に当てはめてください
In this way,
not just on the printed page,
そのようにして印刷されたページや
図書棚にではなく—
not just on the library shelf,
but in our minds,
in our own hearts,
わたしたちの思いと心に
また自分たちの生活において—
in our own lives
the Word of God
will truly endure forever.
神の言葉はまさに永久に
存続することになるでしょう！
Now, let’s get better acquainted
with one of the individuals
では 先程述べた 神の言葉を真に愛した人を
さらに取り上げましょう
we just mentioned
who truly loved God’s Word.
In the 16th century,
English scholar William Tyndale
16世紀 英国の学者
ウィリアム・ティンダルは—
聖書を翻訳するため 厳しい迫害に
耐えなければなりませんでした
had to endure harsh persecution
in order to translate the Bible.
それでもティンダルは—
But he was convinced
that the Bible had to be translated.
聖書は翻訳されなければならない
と確信していました
You will notice
that this brief documentary
この短いドキュメンタリーは—
has been designed also
to appeal to people
エホバの証人ではない人も
楽しめるよう作られています
who are not
Jehovah’s Witnesses,
as it will later
be made available
後ほど 公式ウェブサイト
jw.orgに掲載されます
on our official website,
jw.org.
In the autumn of 1536,
1536年の秋
ウィリアム・ティンダルは—
William Tyndale was led from his prison cell,
in the castle of Vilvoorde,
刑務所の独房から
ビルボールデ城へ連行されました
to the site of his impending execution.
彼の処刑場です
There a post had been prepared for him.
杭が用意されており
彼は鎖で縛りつけられ—
Tyndale was chained to the post,
絞殺され
遺体は公衆の面前で焼かれました
strangled to death,
and then his body burned
before the onlooking crowd.
彼の罪状は 教会の教えを—
His crime?
Tyndale struggled to reconcile
the teachings of the church
ティンダル自身の聖書の研究に
調和させようと奮闘したことです
with his own studies of the Bible.
ティンダルは 聖書が神の言葉である
との信仰を保ったまま死にました
William Tyndale died
with his faith intact
that the Bible
is the Word of God.
William Tyndale
was the first person to seek
ウィリアム・ティンダルは原語の聖書を—
to translate the Bible
from the original languages
英語に翻訳しようと努めた最初の人でした
into English.
Tyndale was born
in the late 15th century.
ティンダルは 15世紀の終わりごろ—
グロースターシャー近郊で生まれました
He was born
in the area of Gloucestershire
のちにオックスフォードへ行き司祭になりました
but had a chance to go to Oxford
and became a priest.
In the 15th century,
there was a lot of resistance
当時 神の言葉を一般の人々にも
入手しやすくするべきだ—
—the idea that the Word of God
could just simply be accessible
by the general people.
という運動が盛んでした
People knew the Latin Bible from church,
人々は教会で ラテン語聖書の独自の解釈を
司祭から教えられていましたが—
which was interpreted by the priest for them.
They never had direct access
to the Bible themselves.
聖書を直接 手にすることは
ありませんでした
Tyndale was not allowed
to do this translation in England.
イングランドで聖書翻訳は
禁じられていました
He went to the Bishop of London
そこで ティンダルは
ロンドン司教に許可を求めました
asking for his permission
to translate the New Testament
新約聖書を原語のギリシャ語から
英語に翻訳するためです
from the Greek
—the original text—
into English
but was not given that permission.
しかし 許可はおりませんでした
Such was the opposition
to Bible translation
聖書翻訳に対する反対がとても激しかったので—
that Tyndale later wrote
that there was
ティンダルはのちに—
no place to do it in all England.
翻訳できる場所は イングランドのどこにも
なかったと述べています
And so with the help of merchants
sympathetic to his cause,
その後 彼の活動に賛同する
商人たちからの援助もあり—
Tyndale fled to Germany
where he could more easily work
新約聖書の英訳に取り組みやすい
ドイツへ逃げました
on his English translation
of the New Testament.
By 1525,
1525年には翻訳が完成し
印刷の用意ができました
his translation was complete
and ready to be printed.
The British Library in London
holds the answer
ロンドンの大英図書館には—
その後 どうなったかを
示すものが残されています
to what happened next.
Dr. Karen Limper-Herz,
a lead curator at the library,
主任学芸員のカレン・リンパーヘルツ博士
にお聞きしましょう
is going to help us find out.
So we are looking
at a unique copy of the first edition
これは ティンダルの新約聖書の
貴重な初版で—
of Tyndale’s New Testament,
printed in Cologne in 1525.
1525年にケルンで印刷されました
The Cologne Fragment
is the only known copy
ケルン断片はティンダル訳の初版として
唯一現存しているものです
of what exists of Tyndale’s first edition
of the New Testament.
これが断片だという事実は
危険な作業だったことを示しています
The fact that it is a fragment
shows that it was a dangerous thing to do.
The printer had too much to drink
酒に酔った印刷業者が
“自分はティンダルのために—”
and mentioned that he
was printing
this pro-Lutheran English New Testament
“親ルター派の英訳聖書を印刷している”
ともらしてしまいました
for somebody called William Tyndale.
それを知った当局は
印刷所を襲撃しました
The authorities found out about it,
and the print shop was raided.
ティンダルたちはライン川をたどり
ウォルムスへ逃げ—
Tyndale and his partners ran
—and this is all that survives today—
そのときの断片が
現在まで生き延びています
and they went down the Rhine
a bit further to Worms.
彼らがマタイによる書しか
手にしていないことも—
So the fact that they didn’t get much further
than part way through Matthew
危険な作業だったことを示しています
is quite indicative
of how dangerous it was.
The first complete copies
of Tyndale’s translation
ティンダル訳の最初の
クリスチャン・ギリシャ語聖書は—
of the Christian Greek Scriptures
were finally printed
最終的に 1526年
ドイツのウォルムスで印刷されました
in the city of Worms in Germany
in 1526.
それから3000冊以上出版されたのです
Around 3,000 or more
of these books were produced.
After leaving Germany,
ドイツを離れた後 ティンダルは
アントワープに向かいました
Tyndale moved to Antwerp.
この活気ある都市は
彼にとって理想の地でした
This bustling city
was ideal for Tyndale.
It had a thriving printing industry
印刷産業が盛んで—
and its busy port
往来の盛んな港からイングランドへ
聖書を届けやすくなったのです
made it easy for his books
to reach readers in England.
Professor Guido Latré
has kindly offered to show me
グイド・ラトレ教授は およそ500年前に
ティンダル自身が歩いたであろう—
around the very streets that Tyndale
would have walked himself
まさにその道を案内してくれました
some 500 years ago.
What he saw around him here
were ordinary people
彼はここで 普通の人が聖書を母語で
手にしている様子を目にし—
having access to the Bible in Dutch.
故郷のイングランドでも
同じようにしたいと思いました
He wanted the same
for his own folk in England.
イングランドに
大量の聖書をひそかに送るのに—
If you wanted to smuggle Bibles
on a large scale into England,
北ヨーロッパ最大の港町は
ちょうど良い場所でした
this was Northern Europe’s biggest seaport.
大きな本をそのままひそかに送るのは
簡単なことではありません
You can’t easily smuggle
a big volume and a big format.
そこで 細かくページを分けて—
So tiny loose leaves
地下倉庫や貯蔵所などに
持ち込まれました
that were taken to places like this
—these underground cellars,
the warehouses—
そして 発禁文書ではない
大きな本の間に—
and between the leaves
of larger books
that were not forbidden,
ティンダル訳の小さなページが
隠されたようです
the tiny leaves of Tyndale’s translation
would have been hidden.
ロンドンで ある人たちは
“あぁ これが例の本だ！—”
In London,
someone would have recognized:
‘Aha!
These are the stacks that are marked.
“よく見て この中から
ティンダルの聖書のページを見つけないと”—
‘I must have a look at these
と気づいたことでしょう
and find the loose leaves
of Tyndale’s Bible.’
彼の生涯の終わりまでには—
There were about 30,000 copies
3万冊ものティンダル訳が
入手できるようになりました
of Tyndale’s Bible available
勇気においても 費やした時間の点でも
彼は勇敢で偉大な人物です
by the end of his life.
This was a brave man
and a big man in terms of courage
and in terms of investment of time.
また おかした危険も過小評価できません
And the risks he took
are not to be underestimated.
ウィリアム・ティンダルはブリュッセルの北にある
ビルボールデで投獄されました
William Tyndale was imprisoned here
in Vilvoorde,
just north of Brussels.
As he languished
in prison for over a year,
１年以上 獄中で過ごしている間—
he no doubt contemplated the cruel death
that inevitably awaited him.
残酷な死が待ち受けていることを
予期していたことでしょう
ティンダルは
英語に影響を与えた人として有名です
Tyndale is often renowned
for his influence on the English language,
しかし 彼の働きは
学問的な志だけによるのではありません
but his work was more than
that of just scholarly ambition.
Tyndale loved the Bible.
ティンダルは聖書を愛していました
神の言葉について述べた詩編作者と
同じ気持ちだったと言えるでしょう
Maybe it can be said of him
that he shared the feelings of the psalmist
who spoke of God’s Word
“わたしはどんなにあなたの律法を
愛していることでしょう”
and said:
“How I do love your law!”
激しい迫害にもかかわらず—
Despite intense opposition,
聖書とその知恵は
今日まで生き残っており—
the Bible and the wisdom in it
survives to this day,
著者の言葉を忠実に伝えているのです
a faithful transmission
of the original writers’ words.
多くの人が聖書を大切にしてきたのも
不思議ではありません
No wonder so many have placed
such value on the Bible.
You’ll be happy to know
that later this month
嬉しいことに このドキュメンタリーの
長編版が今月中に公開されます
an extended version
of this documentary
will be made available.
It contains
additional examples of individuals
命をかけて神の言葉を広めた
ほかの人たちの例も収められています
who risked their lives
to spread God’s Word.
The video is called
They Valued the Bible
“聖書を大切にした人たち”
と題するビデオで—
ビデオ・オンデマンドの
“聖書”の見出しに掲載されます
and will be released
on Video on Demand
under the heading
“The Bible.”
Knowing that Jehovah
is personally involved
エホバがみ言葉を保存し 広めることに
直接関わっておられることを知ると—
in preserving
and making known his Word,
we can be confident
that the Bible
聖書こそ 神に近づく
唯一の正しい方法であると確信できます
is the only true means
of drawing close to him.
As a child,
英国出身のデービッド・シブレーは—
David Sibrey, from England,
had not read the Bible.
子どもの頃 聖書を読んだことがなく
人間の伝統を教えられていました
Instead, he had been taught
traditions of men.
何が真理を理解する
助けになったでしょうか？
What helped him see the truth?
I was born in 1930.
わたしは1930年に生まれ
リトルハンプトンで暮らしました
We lived in Littlehampton,
which was a seaside town,
海のそばで
気持ちの良い静かな場所です
a very pleasant little place,
quiet place.
I would like to walk
in the countryside.
よく 歩いて田舎の方に行きました
Nature intrigued me.
何かを読むより
自然を見るほうが好きなんです
My interest was in what I saw
rather than what I read.
Well, in 1939,
1939年 戦争が始まりました
war broke out, and our road
became the second line of defense.
わたしの町も巻き込まれ
戦闘機が飛び交うようになります
And then, of course,
you get the aircraft.
Well, there was a young boy
(younger than myself),
ある年下の男の子がいました
and one Sunday morning
an air raid took place,
日曜日の朝 空爆があって
その子の家は破壊され—
and the house
where he was living
その子も亡くなったんです
was destroyed,
and he was killed.
But I remember
saying to my mother,
母に聞いた覚えがあります
“どうして死んじゃったの？”
“Why did he have to die?”
And her answer was:
母は “天国で神様と一緒になったのよ”
と言いました
“Well, he’s in a better place.
He’s with God in heaven,”
でも 意味が分かりません
その子を死ぬようにしたのが神様だなんて
which didn’t quite
add up to me.
I couldn’t understand
how God
could be responsible
for his death,
そうだとしたら 戦争も神様のせいです
which meant
He was responsible for war.
So it was—
The whole thing was depressing;
気は晴れませんでした
でも そう考えることにしました
perhaps put it that way.
As far as religion was concerned,
宗教は まあ良いものだろうけど—
I accepted it was there,
していることと一致していない
と思っていました
but I couldn’t understand
how it fit in with what was going on.
どこかずれていて自分のために
なるとも思えませんでした
There was a gap somewhere,
and I couldn’t, I couldn’t, plug it.
Every time you went to church,
賛美歌の本や祈祷書は
教会に持っていくのに—
you had a hymnbook
and a prayer book,
but a Bible was something
you had personally.
聖書はただ自分で
持っているだけなんです
And the only time
I ever opened it
エホバの証人と研究して
初めて聖書を開きました
was when I began to study
with Jehovah’s Witnesses.
I was 17 or 18 years of age
when I started.
17歳か18歳の時
ジョー・グラッドウィン兄弟が来てくれました
A brother named Joe Gladwin
called upon me.
わたしは聖書を全く知らなかったんです
I knew nothing about the Bible.
The fact that he said it,
fair enough.
反論するつもりはなかったんですが
兄弟は聖書にこうある と言うけど—
He said it was in the Bible, OK.
But what do other people say?
ほかの人たちの考えも
確かめようと思いました
I decided to look for myself.
I realized that what Joe
was telling me was right.
そして やっぱり兄弟の言うとおりで
聖書が正しいと分かったんです
He showed me
that the Bible was true.
I began to see that the Bible
今まで知らなかったことを
聖書から学びました
told me things
that I had never known.
Over the years,
I’ve been privileged
これまで長きにわたって
様々な翻訳の聖書を集めてきました
to collect so many
different translations of the Bible.
Reading through the different translations,
いろいろな翻訳を読むと—
it’s clear that God’s Word never changes.
神の言葉は変わっていない
ということが分かります
I got baptized
at the age of 20 in 1950.
1950年
20歳でバプテスマを受けました
Over the years,
I’ve served first of all as a pioneer.
まず 正規開拓奉仕を始め
そして ベテルに来ました
From then I came to Bethel.
Moving from Bethel
to the circuit and district work,
その後 ベテルを出て
巡回 地域の奉仕をし—
and then finally,
coming back to Bethel for the Writing Desk.
今は ベテルの執筆デスクで
奉仕しています
The assignments I’ve had
受けた割り当てを通して
確信を強められてきました
have strengthened my conviction
not only that Jehovah
エホバが指示を与えておられ
聖霊の助けがあれば—
is giving direction and his spirit
can enable us to do
エホバが願っておられることを
何でも行なえます
whatever he wants us to do
but that the organization has grown and,
それだけでなく—
この組織は統治体の指導のもとに
成長を続けてきました
with the development
of the Governing Body’s direction,
is an organization
which is second to none.
このような組織はほかにありません
And, therefore,
staying with it is the logical thing to do.
この組織にとどまり続けるべきなんです
In my life,
I looked in many places
人生にかかわる疑問の答えを
いろいろ探しました
for answers
to life’s questions,
そして 聖書だけが答えてくれました
but only the Bible
has provided answers.
I am so thankful
that Jehovah continues to teach us.
エホバがずっと教えてくださっている
ことに感謝しています
Brother Sibrey’s appreciation
for the Bible is heartwarming.
シブレー兄弟の
聖書への感謝に心を打たれます
Do you remember how
we can personally demonstrate
神の言葉への感謝を表す方法を
覚えていますか？
our appreciation
for the Word of God?
By reading,
studying, and meditating
読み 研究し 収められている
深い考えを黙想し—
on the deep thoughts
that it contains
そして 聖霊を受けて書かれた教えを
生活に当てはめることによってです
and then by applying
those inspired teachings
in our lives.
When we do that,
そうするとき
聖霊が自分の内面に影響を与え—
we allow the holy spirit
to affect our inner being,
願いや人生の目的を形作ってくれます
to shape our desires
and objectives in life.
However, what if someone
has harbored resentment
しかし 仲間の人間に対して
長年憤りを抱き—
against his fellow man
for years,
殺したいと思うほどなら
どうでしょうか？
perhaps to the point
of wanting to kill that person?
そのような深刻な状況で
神の言葉は何ができるでしょうか？
What can God’s Word do
in such a serious circumstance?
Remember the words
of Hebrews 4:12:
ヘブライ 4章12節を思い出して下さい
“For the word of God
is alive and exerts power
“神の言葉は生きていて 力を及ぼし—”
. . . and is able to discern
thoughts and intentions of the heart.”
“心の考えと意向とを
見分けることができるのです”
Yes, Jehovah
has preserved the Bible
そうです エホバは聖書を保存し—
so that we can benefit
from the power of his Word.
神の言葉の力を実感できる
ようにしてくださいました
Vladimir Olkhov
and Valery Zaporozhsky,
ロシアのウラジミール・オリホフと
ヴァレリー・サポロジスキーは—
who are from Russia,
were the fiercest of enemies,
憎み合う敵同士でしたが
その力をじかに経験しました
yet they experienced
that power firsthand.
I was the ringleader of a criminal gang.
わたしはギャングのリーダーでした
We extorted money,
put people out of business,
人から金を奪い取り 誘拐して脅し
放り出しました
threatened them,
dragged them away.
And they would hand over everything.
みんな言いなりになり
わたしを恐れていました
People were afraid of me,
and I liked it that way.
快感でした
I never forgave anybody.
歯向かう人間は
決して許しませんでした
If someone wronged me,
こう言いました—
I would say:
“Throw one stone at me!
“石を投げつけてみろ！
お前を山に埋めてやる！”
I’ll bury you in a mountain of rocks!”
In 1993,
I was working for the police.
1993年 警官として—
They assigned me to gather information
ギャングとリーダーである
ウラジミールの情報収集に—
about a gang
whose leader was Vladimir Olkhov.
割り当てられました
ある時 警官が
わたしを捕まえに来ました
One time, when committing a crime,
they caught me at the scene.
I swore revenge on everybody involved
with my arrest.
奴らに復しゅうしてやる と誓いました
During interrogations,
I did everything
尋問中 ウラジミールをけなし
打ちのめしてやろうとしました
to humiliate Vladimir
and tried to break him.
お互いに憎んでいたんです！
We just hated each other!
I told Valery,
“Just remember:
ヴァレリーに言いました—
“Sooner or later
I’m getting out of prison
“覚えていろ！
牢屋から出たらお前を殺してやる！”
and then you’re a dead man!”
I thought to myself:
‘For a start,
手始めに 奴の車を爆破し
それでもだめなら—
‘I’m going to blow up his car.
If he doesn’t understand,
then I’ll just eliminate him.’
殺してやろう と考えていました
彼の脅しが本気だったので
命の危険を感じました
His threats sounded so serious
that I started to fear for my life.
I decided to have my friends
and acquaintances
仲間に頼んで彼の監視を強化し—
make his life behind bars unbearable
and to make sure
that he would never get out.
決して脱獄しないようにさせました
I saw that one of my cell mates
had a pocket New Testament.
同じ監房に入っていた一人が
新約聖書を持っていたので—
I asked him if I could read it.
読んでいいか尋ねました
Seeing my interest in spiritual things,
関心があるのを知ってか
誰かが“ものみの塔”誌をくれました
someone gave me a Watchtower magazine.
読むにつれて 自分とは違う
本当の人たちがいることが分かりました
When I started reading the magazine,
I realized that there are
other people out there—real people.
There’s a totally different way
of life to be had, even now,
全く違う生き方
将来の希望を持っている人たちです
and with such prospects.
I was just stunned.
衝撃でした
Then I found another five magazines
around the prison.
牢屋の周りで
他の5冊の雑誌を見つけました
I devoured them as well.
読みふけりました
And I became thoroughly convinced
that I had found the truth.
真理を見つけたと強く確信しました
妻との面会が初めて許された時
“真理を見つけたぞ！” と言いました
When my wife was first allowed to visit me,
I told her right away,
“I’ve found the truth!”
妻は急速に進歩し
2年後にバプテスマを受けました
My wife made pretty fast progress
and was baptized two years later.
妻の支えは貴重でした
Her support was invaluable.
毎回訪ね 正直に そして
神に忠実であるよう力づけてくれました
She would visit me,
constantly encouraging me
to be faithful
and remain loyal to God.
In 1993,
Jehovah’s Witnesses visited me.
1993年に証人が訪ねてきました
I agreed to a Bible study,
but the truth didn’t touch my heart.
聖書研究には同意しましたが
心には響きませんでした
One time, Jehovah’s Witnesses
invited me to a gathering,
ある時 集まりに誘われ—
ウラジミールが
エホバの証人になるために—
and there they told me that Vladimir Olkhov
バプテスマを受けようとしていると
知らされました
—that criminal—
was about to get baptized
and become one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
あの犯罪者がです
I was cut to the heart!
ショックでした
家に帰って泣き崩れました
When I got home,
I burst into tears.
I realized that I had to make
spiritual progress.
霊的に進歩しなければと感じました
Because if he,
in his circumstances,
彼にできるのなら
わたしにもできるはずだからです
could do it, then I could do it.
人生で初めて祈ったのは
まさにその時でした
That very moment,
I prayed for the first time in my life.
I was released in October of 1997.
1997年10月に釈放されました
After I was released,
the brothers organized a gathering.
釈放後 兄弟たちは
ある集まりを設けました
They invited me to this gathering.
兄弟たちは
その集まりに招待してくれました
I remember
that as I was approaching the place,
着いてみると わたしがかつて
家宅捜査をした場所だと気づいたんです
I suddenly realized this is where
I once conducted a search!
And then Valery walked into the room.
ヴァレリーが部屋に入ってくると—
わたしたちは抱き合って
声をあげて泣きました
We just hugged each other
and burst into tears.
彼の目は 以前とは
まったく違っていました
And I saw in his eyes
a completely different look,
not like before
—it was a kind look.
優しい目でした
It brought tears to my eyes.
胸から重荷が
取り除かれた感じがしました
It was like a big weight
was lifted from my chest.
‘My brother!’
“兄弟！” お互いに許しを求めました
We begged one another for forgiveness.
On the 23rd of November 1997,
1997年11月23日—
I was baptized together in the same pool
バプテスマを受けました
同じプールで ヴァレリーと！
as my new friend Valery.
わたしたちは真の友となりました
We really became the best of friends.
今では同じ会衆で二人とも長老です
And now we serve as elders
in the same congregation.
My wife and I often talk about
妻とわたしはよく—
もし聖書を勉強していなかったら
どうなっていただろうと話します
what would have happened to us
if we had not started to study the Bible.
Probably we wouldn’t even be alive now.
多分 今頃は生きていなかったでしょう
We’ve kept our family together.
今でも家族と一緒です
Even better,
we now have a spiritual family
更に 霊的な家族を
クリスチャン会衆内に持っています
in the Christian congregation.
And my former enemy
is now my brother and best friend.
かつての敵は
今では兄弟であり親友です
More importantly, we’ve developed
大切なこととして
エホバとの良い関係を持っているんです
a close relationship with Jehovah.
Only God is able to change the thinking
神だけが
彼のような根っからの犯罪者や—
of such bitter enemies as Vlad and I were.
わたしのような者をも
変化させることができます
And I eagerly look forward to the day
わたしは分裂が永遠になくなることを
心から願っています
when everything that divides people
will be gone forever.
Do you see
one reason why Jehovah
エホバが ご自分の言葉が消されない
ようにされた理由に気づきましたか？
did not allow his Word
to be obliterated?
He knew the benefits
you and I would reap
聖書を読むことが—
どれほどわたしたちのためになるか
ご存じなのです
from having access to the Bible.
Its message is so powerful,
そのメッセージは非常に強力なので—
it could help Vladimir and Valery
ウラジミールとヴァレリーは
生き方を変え 親友にまでなりました
to change their lives
and even become close friends.
While very few of us have taken part
in the translation of the Bible,
聖書翻訳に携わる人はごく少数ですが—
わたしたちは皆
近所の人に聖書を分かち—
all of us can share it with our neighbors
エホバについての正確な知識を
得るよう助けることができます
and help them to gain
accurate knowledge of Jehovah.
In the following dramatization,
次のドラマで
家族が楽しんでいる神権的活動と—
note some of the theocratic activities
that this family enjoys
熱意を持てるよう何を行なう必要が
あったかに注目してください
and what they had to do
to become so zealous.
OK, OK.
ちょっと待った
We already know
how this story is going to end.
これは このストーリーの結末部分です
No real surprises there.
でも大切なのは どうやって
ここまで来ることができたのか です
So the real question is,
How did we get here?
For the record,
家族の宣教に援助が必要だとは
思ってもみませんでした
I never thought our ministry
really needed help.
My wife and daughter
were both regular pioneers.
妻も娘も 開拓者だし—
My son was a solid publisher.
息子も ちゃんとした伝道者
わたしも まだ開拓はできないけど
家族のためになんでもやってきました
And while my schedule
didn’t let me pioneer yet,
I was trying to do
all I could to support them.
I always assumed
できるだけ一緒に奉仕に出る事が—
the best support I could provide
was just being out with them
家族のためにできる最善の事だと
思い込んでいました
as much as possible,
でも もっと必要なことがあると
気づかされたんです
but I quickly realized more was needed.
ここ数週間 野外奉仕の群れの監督は—
Our Field Service Group Overseer
had been making a real effort
わたしたち家族と一緒に奉仕するよう
真剣に努力してくれて—
to work in the ministry with us
regularly the last few weeks,
いくつかの課題に
親切に気づかせてくれました
and he kindly mentioned
he’d noticed a few challenges.
While our service time was great,
奉仕時間はよく入っているけど
再訪問が少しずつ減っていること—
he pointed out that our return visits
were slowly dwindling.
And other than the studies
I had with the children,
子どもとの研究以外 家族のだれも—
no one in the family
was conducting a Bible study.
研究司会をしていないことに
注意を向けてくれたんです
I asked him
what we could do to try
わたしは宣教の質を
改善するために何ができるか—
and improve
the quality of our ministry.
兄弟に尋ねてみました
兄弟はローマ 15章19節の
パウロの言葉を見せてくれました
He showed me Romans 15:19,
highlighting Paul’s words:
“わたしは キリストについての
良いたよりを徹底的に宣べ伝えました”
“I have thoroughly preached
the good news about the Christ.”
He suggested
on our next Family Worship night
それから 次の家族の崇拝で
パウロの宣教を研究して—
studying Paul’s ministry and seeing
what we could learn from his example.
その模範から学ぶのはどうか
と勧めてくれたんです
パウロの宣教を調べるにつれて—
As we looked at Paul’s ministry,
we realized
産出的な奉仕に必要なものが
分かりました
to be more productive
we needed boldness.
大胆さです
Ephesians 6:19 says:
エフェソス 6章19節には—
“そして わたしのためにも祈ってください”
“Pray also for me,
“that the words may be given to me
when I open my mouth,
“わたしが口を開くときに
話す能力を与えられ—”
“so that I may be able to speak boldly
“はばかりのないことばで
良いたよりの神聖な奥義を—”
in making known
the sacred secret of the good news.”
“知らせることができるように
するためです”とあります
Rina also noticed how Paul
娘の璃菜は パウロが説得力ある仕方で
人々と論じ合ったことに注目しました
reasoned persuasively with people.
妻の恵子は 相手との共通の土台を
築く仕方に注目しました
And Keiko liked how he found
common ground with those he talked to
—even referring to a pagan altar
to an unknown god
パウロは 会話を
エホバの方に導くために—
知られていない異教の神の祭壇さえ
使ったのです
as a way to direct
the conversation to Jehovah.
Finally, Haruto noted how 2 Timothy said
そして春斗は テモテ第二でパウロが
“恥ずべきところのない働き人として”—
Paul was
“a workman with nothing to be ashamed of,
“真理の言葉を正しく”用いた点に
注目しました
handling the word of the truth aright.”
So he was skilled in using the Scriptures
with those he witnessed to.
パウロは宣教で聖句を使うのが
巧みだったのです
See, I told you.
もうお分かりでしょう
これが このストーリーの結末
だったのです
You already knew
how this was going to end.
I started auxiliary pioneering.
わたしは補助開拓奉仕を始めました
We now have a number of return visits
今では 家族でたくさんの再訪問を行ない
進歩的な研究生も何件か見つけました
and a few progressive Bible studies.
でも どうやってここまで
来たのでしょうか？
But how did we get here?
家族でパウロから学びました
We learned from the example of Paul
その模範と彼がどのように
徹底的に証ししたかをね
and how he
“thoroughly preached the good news.”
The group overseer
could’ve simply listed
群れの監督は
家族の宣教の改善に必要なことを—
what changes were needed
to improve the family’s ministry.
単に列挙することもできました
Instead,
he directed the father
しかし 聖書中の特定の原則に
父親の注意を向けました
to a specific principle
found in the Scriptures.
After all,
it is only God’s Word
結局 神の言葉だけが
教えるために“霊感を受け”ています
that “is inspired . . . for teaching.”
Bible translations
in common languages
一般の言語に翻訳された聖書は—
started to spread
across Europe in the 1500’s,
1500年代にヨーロッパ中に
広まり始めました
but it took much longer
しかし さらに遠くの場所では
もっと長い時間がかかりました
for more remote places
to receive the Bible.
It was in 1766
1766年に グリーンランド語の
ギリシャ語聖書—
that the complete Greek Scriptures,
or New Testament,
あるいは新約聖書全体が
初めて出版されました
was first published in Greenlandic
—a language spoken today
by about 50,000 people.
現在 約5万人が
グリーンランド語を話します
In August of last year,
昨年8月 わたしは
スカンディナビア支部が監督する—
I had the privilege of serving
a regional convention in Greenland,
グリーンランドでの
地区大会に出席しました
which is overseen
by the Scandinavia branch.
グリーンランドは
わたしが11年間 開拓奉仕をした—
Greenland is the neighbor
to the north of Newfoundland,
ニューファンドランドの北にあります
where I pioneered for 11 years.
So it was a wonderful experience
to go there and meet our brothers.
それで そこに行って兄弟たちに
会えたのは素晴らしい経験でした
Some 400 brothers and sisters
traveled at their own expense
スカンディナビア各地から
約400人の兄弟姉妹が自費で旅行し—
from all over Scandinavia to support
the convention in Greenland.
グリーンランドでの大会を支えました
Although Greenland is a land
covered by large ice caps,
グリーンランドは広大な氷で
覆われていますが—
真理を慕う温かい心を
持つ人たちが大勢います
there are many warm hearts
yearning for the truth.
I think that Jesus had Greenland in mind
イエスの述べた
“地の最も遠い所”とは—
when he spoke about preaching
to the most distant part of the earth.
グリーンランドなのかもしれません
My name is Arne Mattsson.
アーネ・マトソンです
My wife, Karin, and I have lived
in Greenland for more than 34 years.
妻のカリンと34年以上
グリーンランドで暮らしています
We have traveled all over the country
preaching about God’s Kingdom,
国中を旅行して 神の王国を宣べ伝え—
and we have had
some fantastic experiences.
素晴らしい経験をしてきました
In the 1950’s, two young special pioneers
came to Greenland
グリーンランドの最初の伝道者は—
1950年代に来た
二人の特別開拓者です
as the first publishers.
They traveled by boat
from town to town
船による伝道旅行の持ち物は—
carrying just tents
and simple equipment.
テントと簡単な装備だけでした
They had to endure
the cold weather,
耐えなければならなかったのは—
厳しい寒さ
地元の僧職者の反対—
face resistance
from the local ministers,
and even fight with sledge dogs
that took their food.
そして 食べ物を狙う そり犬
しかし その働きは 国内における—
But they laid the groundwork
for the great effort
後の宣教活動の基礎を
据えるものとなりました
that has been made
to preach to all in this country.
In the 1960’s and ’70’s,
60年代と70年代に—
many families
moved here from Denmark
デンマークからの多くの家族が
宣教のために引っ越して来ました
to help with the preaching work.
I remember how I,
as a teenager in 1971,
わたしが10代だった 1971年に—
moved from Denmark
to Greenland with my family.
わたしの家族も
デンマークから移り住みました
It was not easy
to learn the language,
難しい地元の言語を
兄弟姉妹は一生懸命に学び—
but the brothers and sisters
from Denmark did their best,
それが 区域の人々の
良い反応につながりました
and it had a good effect
on the territory.
In 1973, The Watchtower began
to be published in Greenlandic.
1973年には グリーンランド語の
「ものみの塔」誌が発行され始めました
Just to pronounce the name,
「ナパスリアク・アラペルナールシフィク」
と発音するのも ひと苦労です
Napassuliak’ Alapernaerssuivfik,
was a challenge.
But it has been a popular magazine
in Greenland ever since.
とはいえ 発行以来
グリーンランドでは評判の雑誌です
Once, we met a couple
以前 入植地に住むご夫婦に
お会いしました
who for many years
had received copies of The Watchtower
お二人は長年「ものみの塔」誌を
受け取っていました
when publishers visited their settlement.
They told us that they often felt depressed
when they woke up in the morning,
憂うつな気分で
朝目ざめることの多いお二人は—
but when they read the magazine,
they felt better.
雑誌を読むと気分が良くなるので—
And they would read
the same copies over and over again.
同じ部分を 何度も何度も
読んだとのことでした
When the temperature drops
and the snow falls,
寒くなって 雪が降ると—
the landscape gets covered
半年間も一面が
雪のじゅうたんで覆われるので—
by a beautiful white blanket for half a year,
伝道者にとって夏は働き時です
so the publishers
make good use of the summer.
Some towns and settlements
証言をあまり受けることのない
町や入植地があります
only seldom receive a witness.
There are no roads between the towns,
but we reach isolated areas by boat.
町を結ぶ道路はないので
遠隔地にはボートで行き—
When someone shows interest
in our message,
関心を示した人とは
電話で連絡を取り合います
the contact
is maintained by phone.
Many have great respect for the Bible,
「わたしの聖書物語」の本は—
聖書に深い敬意を抱く
本当に多くの家庭に配布されてきました
and so My Book of Bible Stories
has found its way into many, many homes.
Over a period of 24 years,
Karin and I have sailed so much
24年にわたり わたしたちが
宣教のためにボートで移動した距離は—
that it equals a trip
twice around the globe.
なんと地球2周分です
This has cost a lot of effort and money,
苦労しましたし お金もかかりました
but with Jehovah’s blessing,
でも エホバの祝福により—
we have been able
to continue year after year
この遠い地で 何年にもわたり
宣教を続けることができました
preaching to the distant parts
of Greenland.
The preaching work here
is a great experience.
ここでの宣教活動は
素晴らしい経験になります
People are attentive and kind.
人々はよく耳を傾けてくれて親切です
But it took a long time
before the first native Greenlander
それでも 地元の方が
初めてバプテスマを受けたのは—
was baptized
—actually 18 years of zealous preaching.
熱心な奉仕が行われた
18年後のことでした
Today, there are
more than 150 publishers
今では 5つの会衆に所属する
150人以上の伝道者が奉仕しています
in 5 congregations.
Jehovah has really blessed
60年以上にわたり—
the work that has been done here
for more than 60 years.
エホバはこの地の活動を
確かに祝福してくださいました
In August 2016,
2016年8月 主都のヌークで
文字通り特別な大会が開かれました
a very special convention
was held in the capital of Nuuk.
Brothers and sisters
from all over Scandinavia
スカンディナビアの兄弟姉妹が来て—
わたしたちの大会に出席してくれました
traveled all the way
to attend the convention.
We were very encouraged
信仰を強める話をしてくださった
マーク・サンダーソン兄弟の訪問に—
by the visit of a member
of the Governing Body,
Brother Mark Sanderson,
who gave us
some faith-strengthening talks.
わたしたちは大いに力づけられました
I think it’s a great privilege
真理を理解できるというのは
素晴らしいことです
to be able to understand the truth.
自分のような取るに足りない人間に—
It’s amazing that Jehovah
gave his attention
エホバが注意を向けてくださる
というのは 本当に驚きです
to an insignificant human like me.
When I started to follow
その特異な教えと原則に
従って初めて—
the Bible’s unique teachings
and principles,
聖書が自分の生活の質を
向上させるということを—
I clearly understood
how it would benefit my own life.
はっきり理解できました
After this convention,
even though we live in small towns
世界の他の土地から
遠く離れたわたしたちですが—
far away
from the rest of the world,
今回の大会で—
世界中の兄弟たちが
ぐっと身近になりました
we feel closer than ever before
to the worldwide brotherhood.
The peak attendance
at the convention was 614
大会の最高出席者数は614人で
グリーンランドの最高数でした
—the largest ever in Greenland.
Our brothers
from other parts of Scandinavia
スカンディナビアの他の場所から
出席した兄弟たちも—
who attended
the convention also took part
関心ある人たちを招待する
キャンペーンに参加しました
in a campaign
inviting interested ones.
In only two hours,
たった2時間で
主都ヌークが網羅されました
the whole capital city of Nuuk
was covered.
It was a wonderful witness!
素晴らしい証言でした！
And speaking of witnessing
“地の最も遠い所にまで”
証言することに関連して—
in “the most distant part
of the earth,”
you’ll be happy to know
統治体のジェフリー･ジャクソン兄弟が
最近の朝の崇拝で—
that Brother Geoffrey Jackson
of the Governing Body
recently explained
in a morning worship
19世紀に聖書が数多くの言語に
どのように翻訳されたかを説明しました
how the Bible was translated
into numerous languages
in the 19th century.
“「最も遠い所にまで」達する“
という題で—
That segment is now available
on Video on Demand.
ビデオ・オンデマンドで
今 見ることができます
It is entitled
Reaching “the Most Distant Part.”
And later this month,
今月後半 2011年の年次総会の
素敵なビデオが掲載されます
a beautiful segment
from the 2011 annual meeting
will be posted
for your enjoyment.
It is an interview
夫が統治体の成員だったやもめの姉妹たち
5人へのインタビューです
with five widows
of Governing Body members.
The sisters relate
how they learned the truth
真理を知ったいきさつや—
and share treasured memories
from their many years
長年の忠実な奉仕の
楽しい思い出が話されます
of faithful service.
This segment is entitled
“夫が統治体の成員だった忠実な
姉妹たちへのインタビュー”と題し—
Interview With Faithful Sisters
—Widows of Governing Body Members
ビデオ・オンデマンドの—
and will be available
“経験とインタビュー“の
カテゴリーに掲載されます
on Video on Demand under the
“Interviews and Experiences” category.
Do you agree that Jehovah gave us
エホバは ご自分の言葉を通して—
最高のプレゼントを
与えてくださったと思いませんか？
an outstanding gift in his Word?
He not only gave us the gift
プレゼントを
与えてくださっただけでなく—
but also made sure time and time again
何度も何度も わたしたちのために
保存されるようにしてくださいました
that it was preserved for our benefit.
Individuals we met earlier in the program,
今月のプログラムにあったように—
such as Brothers David Sibrey,
デービッド・シブレー
ウラジミール・オリホフ —
Vladimir Olkhov,
and Valery Zaporozhsky,
ヴァレリー・サポロジスキー
といった兄弟たちは皆—
have all seen
the effects of the power
神の言葉の力と導きを経験しました
that God’s Word exerts
and the guidance it provides.
We also saw that the Bible
使徒パウロの模範に倣って
宣教を改善した家族から—
is “beneficial for teaching”
and “for setting things straight,”
聖書が“教え 物事を正すのに有益”
であることも分かりました
as we watched a family
learn how to improve their ministry
by following the example
of the apostle Paul.
Yes, God’s Word has endured
そうです 神の言葉はこれまで存続し
これからも永久に存続します
and will continue to endure forever.
As you know,
ご存じのとおり 2017年4月3日—
on April 3, 2017,
ウォーウィックにある
ミュージアムが一般公開されます
our museums in Warwick
will open to the public.
In addition
to our enlarged gallery entitled
“聖書と神のみ名”と題する
拡張された展示に加え—
“The Bible and the Divine Name,”
“神の言葉は永久に存続する”
と題する新しい展示もあります
we will also have
a new gallery on the theme
“The Word of God Endures Forever.”
Please come and visit.
どうぞ 見に来てください
You’ll be happy to see
a wonderful collection of Bibles
今回のブロードキャスティングで
扱われた点を例示する—
素晴らしい聖書のコレクションを見て
わくわくすることでしょう
that illustrates the points
we have discussed in this broadcast.
The psalmist was inspired to write:
詩編作者は霊感のもとに—
“How I do love your law!”
“わたしはどんなにあなたの律法を
愛していることでしょう“と書きました
And we agree.
We love Jehovah
and we love the Bible
わたしたちも エホバを愛し
聖書を愛しています
and so have millions
throughout the centuries,
幾世紀もの間 神の言葉を
保存するために用いられた人々を含め—
including those who were used
by Jehovah to preserve his Word.
非常に大勢の人々も愛してきました
With these thoughts in mind,
これを思いにとめ
今月のミュージックビデオ—
let’s enjoy
this month’s music video entitled
“あなたのことば 永遠に”
を楽しみましょう
Your Word Endures Forever.
時を 越えて
They looked up at the stars
With godly fear in their hearts.
明かされてきた
あなたの愛が
They thanked their God up above
For revealing to them His love.
こうして 今 ここに
その名 示し
So You gave them your name,
A Kingdom hope to proclaim.
希望を灯す
輝き 失せず
They’re words preserved for our day.
They’re faithful words to show us the way.
尚も 道 照らして
They loved you from their heart,
And they were proud to play their part—
誓いを 胸に
志 果たし
一言も 失わず
Approved by you to preserve your Word,
Wrote it down so you would be heard.
同じ声 聴いてる
あなたの言葉
Your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
海より 深く
風のように 心そよぎ
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
続く 陽のように
And your sayings I just want to keep.
敵の炎も
Oh, whatever Your enemies tried,
They could not silence You.
決して 奪えない
誇らしく 守り抜く
Your loyal ones who loved your Word
Kept their faith, integrity too.
変わらぬ愛がある
企みに行く手を
And when they tried to ban their Bibles,
They were prepared to give their lives.
封じられようと
命さえも 惜しくはない
For so strong was their faith
and the witness they gave,
沈黙などしない
Not one of your words was erased.
あなたの その言葉
And so your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
海より深く
風のように 心そよぎ
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
続く陽のように
And your sayings I just want to keep.
あなたの名は エホバ
And you told us your name is Jehovah.
In your Word it’s plain to see.
永遠<とわ>に 美しい
湧き上がる 賛美歌う
So your name will endure,
All your words will come true,
命の日の限り
And we’ll praise you all of our days.
決して 色褪せない
So your Word endures forever,
And your sayings are, oh, so deep.
あなたの言葉
青草 枯れ 花 落ちても
The good news you declare
is a breath of fresh air,
続く 永遠に
And your sayings I just want to keep,
永遠に
All of my days.
A beautiful song, indeed!
本当に美しい歌です！
We would like to conclude
マリの兄弟姉妹からのあいさつで
今月のプログラムを閉じましょう
this program
by sharing these greetings
from our brothers and sisters in Mali.
マリは西アフリカに位置し
サハラ砂漠の奥深くにまで及んでいます
Mali is located in western Africa,
reaching well into the Sahara Desert.
The northern part of the country
is hot and covered with sand,
国の北側は暑く
砂に覆われていますが—
but the southern region,
which is watered by the Niger River,
南側はニジェール川で潤い
森林や植物で緑豊かです
is green with forests and vegetation.
The Witnesses in the country
have a huge task,
この国の証人たちには
膨大な仕事があります
as the ratio
of Jehovah’s Witnesses to population
人口に対するエホバの証人の比率は
およそ5万9千人に1人です
is about one publisher
to 59,000 residents.
加えて 途方もない距離があります
Also, the distances are tremendous.
The approximately 300 publishers
およそ300人の伝道者が—
cover an area more than twice
フランスの2倍以上の広さを持つ
地域を網羅しています
the size of the country of France.
Mali is one of the hottest countries
in the world,
マリは世界でも特に暑い国です
so some groups and congregations
そのため 外の涼しい木陰で
集会を開く群れや会衆もあります
hold their meetings outdoors
under the cool shade of a tree.
Although the official language
of the country is French,
公用語はフランス語ですが—
たいていの人は地元の言語である
バンバラ語のほうがよく理解できます
most people better understand
the local language Bambara.
それで ほとんどの集会はバンバラ語で
開かれるか通訳されています
Thus, most meetings are either
held or interpreted in Bambara.
Recently, language classes
were held in Bomu,
最近 別の地元の言語
ボム語の言語クラスが開かれました
which is another local language.
Also, the seven publishers
of the American Sign Language group
さらに アメリカ手話の
群れの7人の伝道者が—
have been assigned to witness
マリに住む35万人以上の聴覚障害者に
証言するよう割り当てられました
to the more than
350,000 people in Mali
who have
a hearing impairment.
Last year, the total attendance
for the Memorial
昨年の記念式の出席者は
合計1100人以上でした
was over 1,100 people.
One man who received an invitation
招待状を受け取ったある男性は—
walked three kilometers,
足が不自由であるにもかかわらず
記念式に出席するため3キロ歩きました
or almost two miles,
to attend the Memorial
despite having
a physical challenge with his foot.
今では定期的に集会に出席し
良い進歩を遂げています
He is now regular at the meetings
and is making good progress.
最近 首都に新しい
王国会館が建てられました
Recently, a new Kingdom Hall
was built in the capital city.
Municipal and state authorities,
市や州の当局者 近所の人
また たくさんの通行人は—
neighbors, and many passersby
have been amazed
at what they have seen,
見たことに感銘を受け
ここで働く兄弟たちを褒めました
and they have praised
the brothers working on the project.
Our brothers and sisters
in Mali send us their love.
マリの兄弟姉妹たちが愛を送っています
We love them,
and we love all of you.
わたしたちも皆さんを愛しています
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcastingでした
This is JW Broadcasting
from the world headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses.